WILLIAM (clip): Well, in my published work on the,
...uh, cosmological argument,
...I always try to
...anticipate
...and respond to objections
...that might be raised against the argument.
[film clip] "It knows what I know."
"It might anticipate this move."
WILLIAM (clip): These criticisms are not found
...in scholarly journals.
Instead, they're found in
...popular critiques of the argument
...on the internet
...and YouTube.
"Upload your video to YouTube or Vimeo"
"...using"
".mov, .avi or, um,"
".mpg files"
WILLIAM (clip): They reach
...thousands of people,
...and they are confidently touted by many
...as delivering crushing
...refutations of the Kalam cosmological argument.
[film clip] "K.O.!"
["K.O.!" echoing]
WILLIAM (clip): These objections
...are very widespread,
...and therefore very influential
Infidel websites
...and YouTube are replete
...with these criticisms.
PAUL (narrating): Okay, forget websites and YouTube.
What if I ask someone who wrote a book on this?
You like books.
Right, Dr. Craig?
♪♪
PAUL (narrating): Welcome to Paulogia,
...where a former Christian
...takes a look at the claims of Christians.
Of all the Christian apologists active today,
...perhaps the most vaunted is
...Dr. William Lane Craig,
...a scholar who has in the past
...addressed me personally,
WILLIAM (clip): He was-
...had a brain-dead Christian faith.
PAUL (narrating): ...and whose most famous argument,
...the Kalam cosmological argument,
...I have covered on this channel,
...but perhaps no one has spent
more time studying Dr. Craig
...than James Fodor,
...author of the book
'Unreasonable Faith:'
'How William Lane Craig'
'Overstates the Case for Christianity'.
JAMES (narrating): And in my view,
...the argument is fatally flawed.
So let's briefly outline five major problems
...with Craig's defense of the Kalam,
...showing how he fails to establish the conclusion
...that the universe had a personal cause.
WILLIAM (clip): Introduction.
JAMES (narrating): The Kalam cosmological argument
...is an argument for the existence of God,
...that Craig developed during his doctoral work
...in the 1970s.
While it can be formulated in various ways,
...here I will consider the following version.
Premise one:
"The universe began to exist."
Premise two:
"If the universe began to exist,"
"...it had a cause."
Premise three:
"If the universe had a cause,"
"...that cause must be a personal agent."
And conclusion:
"A personal agent caused the universe"
"...to begin to exist."
There is a simple form of the Kalam
...which just ends at Premise 2,
...and hence concludes merely
that the universe had a cause.
However, since Craig uses the Kalam
...to demonstrate the existence of God,
...I believe it is important to make
that aspect of the argument explicit
...by including Premise 3.
WILLIAM (clip): Now, I had thought at first, tonight,
...to arrange our
...world's worst objections
...into a sort of 'Top 5' list.
Objection number one.
JAMES (narrating): The problem
of the extent of the present.
Craig has stated that when he talks of the universe
...beginning to exist,
...he means this in a very specific way.
In particular, he means that
the universe came into being
...from a state of non-being.
As Craig said many times,
...this depends on a particular
understanding of the nature of time
...called 'presentism'.
According to this view,
...only the present exists.
The past and the future do not exist.
The past
...consists of a series of moments
which came into being
...and then went out of being,
...while the future consists of a series of moments
...which will come into being
...but haven't yet done so.
So this view of time
...contrasts with a competing view known as a
WILLIAM (clip): ...tenseless theory of time,
...because,
...on this view,
There is no objective present
...or past or future.
Events in time are strung out
...in a line
...in the same way
...that events are in space.
And so, on this view,
...it is not as though,
...um...
...the past was formed one event at a time,
...one occurring after another.
The whole timeline just exists,
...and
...our past is just relative to
where we are on the line,
...and what is earlier than that point,
JAMES (narrating): Under the
tenseless theory of time,
...a universe with a finite age
...would not have come into being from non-being,
...but would simply be
...extended a finite time in the earlier-than direction.
This means that under a tenseless theory of time,
...the universe couldn't have begun to exist
...in the way that Craig believes is
necessary for the Kalam to succeed.
Because of this,
...Craig has stated definitively
...that the Kalam cosmological argument
...presupposes from start to finish
...a theory not of tenseless t- time,
...but of tensed time.
WILLIAM (clip): And that presupposes this 'A' theory.
On a 'B' theory of time,
...nothing really ever
...comes into existence.
But I don't think you could run the Kalam argument.
JAMES (narrating): According to Craig,
...presentism,
...the view that only the present exists,
...is vital for the Kalam to succeed,
...but this leads naturally to the question:
What exactly counts as 'present'?
The problem is that Craig has no
sensible answer to this question.
One possibility is that the present could consist of
...an infinitesimally small instant
...with an infinite collection of subset instants forming
...forming a finite interval,
...like just the set of the real numbers.
But this won't work,
...because it would imply that
actual infinities could exist,
...which conflicts with Craig's
many philosophical arguments
...against the possibility of
an infinitely old universe
...and the impossibility of
an actual infinite series.
So a second possibility
...is that the present could exist
...and consist of a discrete unit of time
...with successive discrete presence
following one after the other
...with no time in between them,
...just like the natural numbers.
One, two, three, and so forth.
But this won't work either,
...as that would mean that somehow God was
...restricted to act only at those discrete moments
...but couldn't act in between them.
And that won't do, because that's a contradiction of
...God's omnipotence.
So, if neither of these possibilities are suitable,
...wha- wh- what's left?
Craig's answer
...is that the present consists of the
...present non-metrical interval,
...the length of which varies
depending on the context.
He describes this as follows.
Quote:
"[...] the extent of the present"
"...depends upon the extent of
the entity described as present."
"The duration stipulated to be present"
"...will be an arbitrary, finite duration"
"...centered on a conceptually specified instant."
End quote.
Craig even says that this interval
can be further divided into
...present, past, and future parts.
Although creative,
...the solution is completely absurd.
Indeed, it is essentially unintelligible.
How could it be the case that we
bring into being a period of time
...just by referring to it?
It seems that, according to Craig's view,
...dinosaurs were brought back to life
...when humans discovered them
and began referring to them.
Also,
...if, as Craig claims, only the present exists,
...then how can there be parts of
the present interval that are past
...and parts that are future, neither of which exist?
How can something both exist
...and not exist?
Craig must resolve the problem
of the extent of the present
...if the Kalam has any chance of succeeding.
WILLIAM: Objection number two.
JAMES (narrating): The problem of the relevance
...of thought experiments about infinity.
Craig provides many philosophical arguments
...for why the universe cannot be infinitely old.
These arguments generally
consist of thought experiments
...which aim to provide illustrations
of absurd or impossible scenarios
...that allegedly follow
...from the assumption that
actual infinities can exist.
Some of these thought experiments,
such as Hilbert's hotel,
...aim to show that
...no truly infinite thing
can exist in the real world.
WILLIAM (clip): He invites us to imagine a hotel
...that has an infinite number of rooms in it.
Moreover, he says, imagine that
...every unit, every room is occupied.
Now, you have to have that firmly
...in mind,
...there is a flesh-and-blood person
...in every single room
...throughout the infinite hotel.
Now, Hilbert says,
...suppose somebody shows up at the
...guest registry,
...wanting to check in.
Um...
The proprietor says,
...of course,
...no problem,
...and he moves the person
who was in Room 1 into Room 2,
...the person who was in
Room 2 he puts in Room 3,
Room 3 he puts in Room 4,
...on out to infinity.
As a result,
...Room 1 now becomes vacant,
...and the new person is easily accommodated.
And yet before he came,
...all the rooms were already full.
JAMES (narrating): Craig argues
...that thought experiments such as this illustrate
...the absurdity of actual infinities,
...hence demonstrating that
they cannot exist in reality.
Another type of thought
experiment focuses specifically
...on infinities produced by processes of
...successive addition of one item to the next.
Since this is the type of process
...which, according to the argument,
...would be involved in giving rise
to an infinitely old universe.
While there are many such thought experiments,
...one fairly simple example is
...how one could
...count down all of the negative numbers,
...ending at today.
WILLIAM (clip): How could anyone count down
...all the negative numbers,
...ending at
...today?
Uh, this seems like an absurd task,
...because before he could count any number,
...he would already have to have counted
...an infinite number of prior numbers.
He just gets driven back and back into the past,
...so that no number ever seems to get counted,
...so how could
...somebody finish his countdown today?
That's the initial
...foray that one- one is asking.
But then the question is, as I say,
...if that's a sufficient condition
for finishing the countdown,
...then why didn't he finish his countdown yesterday?
Or the day before that?
By then, he'd already had an infinite amount of time
...to finish his countdown,
...and so he should already be done.
In fact,
...no matter how far you regress into the past,
...at every point he should have already finished,
...because he's had an infinite amount of time
...to finish the countdown.
JAMES (narrating): Thus, according to Craig,
...we cannot make any sense of an
infinite account arriving at the present
...in any particular time.
From this, Craig concludes
...that we should reject the possibility
of arriving at the present
...after an infinitely long count,
...and hence establishes the impossibility
...of an actual infinite past.
While one can argue the details
...of any particular thought experiment,
...there is more fundamental
problem with such reasoning.
Any specific example of an
absurd or impossible situation
...can only ever show that
...that particular case in question
is absurd or impossible.
For example, Hilbert's hotel shows, at most,
...that infinitely large hotels with movable guests
...are absurd.
Likewise, counting down from infinity
...shows that it is not possible to
begin with an infinitely large set
...and then subtract one element at a time
...to eventually reach zero.
The crucial question, however, is:
Why should we infer from such cases
...that the universe cannot be infinitely old?
The universe is not an infinite hotel,
...nor is there some
...cosmic counter marking down the time
...from infinity past until the present.
Other thought experiments, which
...viewers may have heard about,
...for example the Grim Reaper paradox
...and the Tristram Shandy paradox,
...similarly involve bizarre situations,
...such as an infinitely many Grim Reapers appearing
...or a man writing down an infinitely long diary entry,
...neither of which are entailed
...by an infinitely old universe.
And at the most that these
thought experiments could ever show
...is that certain types of infinities
...or certain situations involving infinities
...are absurd or impossible,
...and not that the universe itself
...must have begun to exist.
Craig has argued that the relevant
aspect of all such scenarios
...is the notion of infinity itself,
...rather than the specific details.
But this can always be disputed.
For example, Hilbert's hotel assumes that
...infinitely many guests can be moved around,
...while past events, of course,
...can't be moved around in this way.
The man counting down from infinity past
...had some starting point that
he began counting down from,
...because, after all, that's how counting works.
Yet an infinitely old universe would
have had no such beginning point.
There is thus always a further question about
...which part of the thought experiment
renders it absurd or impossible,
...and Craig fails to show that this
...must be the notion of infinity itself.
This is a fundamental weakness
of this type of argument.
Why should we infer that, because
...certain situations involving
actual infinities are impossible,
...that therefore the universe
...cannot be infinitely old?
WILLIAM (clip): Objection number three.
JAMES (narrating): The problem
of the difference between
...physical and metaphysical time.
To supplement his philosophical arguments,
...Craig also appeals to various
results from contemporary cosmology
...to argue that the best empirical evidence
...supports the beginning of the universe.
The result he most often appeals to is called
...the Borde, Guth, and Vilenkin theorem.
WILLIAM (clip): The Borde, Guth, and Vilenkin theorem
...proves that classical space-time,
...under a single, very general condition,
...cannot be extended to past infinity,
...but must reach a boundary
...at some time in the finite past.
JAMES (narrating): From this
and other related results,
...Craig infers that:
WILLIAM (clip): Modern cosmology
...tells us that
...the universe is not eternal,
...but that
...physical space and time, matter and energy,
...came into existence at the
...point of the Big Bang a finite time ago.
JAMES (narrating): The problem with all such arguments
...is that the Borde, Guth, and Vilenkin theorem,
...along with all modern cosmology,
...is founded upon the general theory of relativity.
In general relativity,
...time is treated as a fourth dimension
...alongside the three dimensions of space,
...which can be bent by the
existence of massive objects
...and is affected by relativistic effects
...such as time dilation.
Time is treated in a tenseless manner,
...with all times existing alongside one another
...in a four-dimensional space-time.
It is very difficult to see how this notion of time
...can be reconciled to Craig's
presented philosophy of time,
...according to which
...the present is an objective feature of reality,
...independent of the matter within the universe,
...and that the past and the future do not exist.
Indeed, in his publications on the philosophy of time,
...Craig himself acknowledges this,
...arguing, for example, that:
WILLIAM (clip): Metaphysical time
...would be time that is not dependent
...upon physical clocks.
It would exist
...and pass,
...independent of
...any physical
...realities or mechanisms.
It's what Isaac Newton called 'absolute time',
...and Newton believed that absolute time
...flows,
...uh, necessarily,
...independent of any physical processes whatsoever.
And I think
...that we have a kind of knockdown argument
...for the difference between
metaphysical and physical time,
...in the thought experiment of God counting down
...to the moment of creation.
JAMES (narrating): He is also clear that
the four-dimensional space-time
...used in general relativity,
...quote,
..."serves as a convenient
calculational and diagrammatical aid,"
"...but says absolutely nothing about ontology."
WILLIAM (clip): Thinking of reality
in four-dimensional terms
...makes
...the special and general theories of relativity
...very easy to grasp.
It's easy to make a space-time diagram
...on a piece of paper,
...in which the horizontal
...dimension represents space
...and the vertical dimension represents time,
...and you can represent the
whole process there on a diagram,
...which depicts spacetime.
And I think many scientists interpret the diagrams
...as literal representations of reality.
JAMES (narrating): "The four-dimensional continuum"
"...should therefore be regarded as a useful tool,"
"...but not as a physical reality,"
...end quote.
This means that Craig faces a stark choice.
If he holds firm to his presented philosophy of time,
...then he must give up all the arguments,
...such as the Borde, Guth, and Vilenkin theorem,
...for the finitude of the past
...that are based on physical cosmology.
On the other hand, if he wishes
to keep using these arguments,
...then he must give up presentism,
...the very philosophy of time that he believes
is essential for the Kalam to succeed.
WILLIAM (clip): Objection number four.
JAMES (narrating): The problem of
establishing a cause of the universe.
Craig believes that:
WILLIAM (clip): The beginning of
the universe must be the effect
...of a first cause.
JAMES (narrating): Well, this may
seem reasonable on the face of it.
On further examination, it is
actually very hard to see
...how Craig could possibly know such a thing.
The most common argument Craig
presents in favor of this contention
...is simply that it is a basic
metaphysical principle that
WILLIAM (clip): Something cannot come out of nothing.
JAMES (narrating): Yet this is begging the question.
Someone who doubts that the universe had a cause
...will not simply accept that
...this is a basic metaphysical principle.
Furthermore, Craig's talk of:
WILLIAM (clip): ...something coming from nothing
JAMES (narrating): ...is inaccurate,
...as this wording implies that
...somehow there was nothing,
...and then:
WILLIAM (clip): ...the universe
just popped into being.
JAMES (narrating): As Craig often says,
...yeah, clearly this doesn't make any sense.
There wasn't anything.
No time or space
...before the universe,
So it wasn't as if there was black emptiness,
...and then suddenly there was a loud pop,
...and the universe appeared.
Rather, the idea is that
...if you could somehow go back to the first moment in time,
...the universe was just already there
...and didn't require anything to make it exist.
It just existed all by itself
without any external cause.
It appears that Craig has nothing to say
...about this more reasonable conception of universe
...that began without a cause.
A second argument that Craig
gives in support of the idea
...that the universe had to have a cause
...is that we have overwhelming evidence from science
...and everyday experience,
...that when something begins
to exist, it has a cause.
Craig therefore argues, by analogy,
...it is therefore reasonable to
believe that the universe as a whole
...must have also had a cause.
Such an inference, however, is simply not warranted.
Everything we observe in science and in everyday life
...is some object or process that exists
...within the universe.
The universe as a whole is not analogous
...to some particular thing within the universe,
...and so we have no reason to think that
...just because things within
the universe have causes,
...that therefore the universe
as a whole must also have a cause.
This is similar to inferring that because
...every man has a mother,
...that therefore mankind as a whole
...must also have a mother.
Craig's third and final argument
that the universe had a cause
...asks the question:
If universes could come into
existence without a cause,
...then why not anything?
Craig asks:
WILLIAM (clip): Why don't bicycles
...and Beethoven
...and root beer
...come into being out of nothing?
JAMES (narrating): But the answer
to such questions is obvious.
Bicycles and Beethoven and root beer
...are things that exist within the universe,
...and have known necessary causes
for their coming into being.
By contrast, the universe is not something
that exists within the universe,
...and does not have no necessary causes,
...but instead is just the totality
of space and time and matter itself,
...for which it is unknown whether
there is any necessary cause.
It is therefore entirely unsurprising
...that things do not pop
into being within the universe.
This doesn't tell us anything about whether
the universe itself required a cause,
...since obviously the universe would not have
...come into being inside the universe,
...because that doesn't make any sense.
Craig's arguments notwithstanding,
...the question therefore remains:
Why couldn't the universe
simply begin without a cause?
WILLIAM (clip): Objection number five.
JAMES (narrating): The problem of
non-personal timeless causes.
Building upon the first two premises of the Kalam,
...Craig also argues that if the universe had a cause,
...that cause must be a personal agent.
Craig argues
...that only an immaterial mind
...with libertarian free will
...could have the ability to bring about
...the beginning of a temporal series of events.
I create the universe
...from an existing timeless state.
To justify this, Craig argues first
...that the cause of the universe
obviously can't be an event in time,
...because then this would
just be part of the universe,
...and would require its own cause.
He also argues that the cause of the universe
...could not have been an impersonal timeless state
...because any effect caused by such a state
...would have to be co-eternal with the cause.
WILLIAM (clip): Why did the effect
only begin a finite time ago?
If the cause is eternal,
...how can you have
...an eternal cause
...but an effect that only has
a beginning a finite time ago?
JAMES (narrating): According to Craig, therefore,
...only an agent with libertarian free will
...could exist timelessly,
...and then, by exercising their libertarian agency,
...bring about an effect that exists in time.
Such an explanation leads naturally to the question:
What is so special about libertarian agency?
Why can't some
...timeless non-personal entity
be the course of the universe?
Why does it have to be a personal agent?
Craig's answer is simply that
...libertarian agents have a
special type of causal power
...called agent causation,
...and only agent causation
...can bring about a temporal
effect from a timeless cause.
Why is that the case?
Craig doesn't appear to have
any clear answer for this,
...other than his assertion that
...this is just the way it is.
For example, he claims:
WILLIAM (clip): A personal agent
...who is endowed with freedom of the will
...and who can therefore freely will
...to create spontaneous, new effects
...that aren't determined by any prior,
...uh, antecedent conditions.
So,
...the
...cause of the universe
...can be a personal agent who freely wills
...to create a universe with a beginning,
...and this
...act of creating is a freely willed act
...that doesn't have any prior determining conditions,
...so it can be something
...that's spontaneous and new.
Uh, for example,
...to return to our illustration, let's imagine
...a- a man who has been sitting from eternity,
...and he suddenly wills to stand up.
And so you would have an effect
...with the beginning, namely his standing,
...arise from a cause
...which is
...eternal and has always been there.
JAMES (narrating): Effectively, this amounts to asserting that
...agent causation,
...and only agent causation,
...can bring about a temporal effect
...from a non-temporal initial state,
...because agent causation is just special that way.
Needless to say, I do not find this
to be a very persuasive argument.
Indeed, I can see no reason
...why any sort of timeless cause
...could not function as a course of the universe.
Why could the cause not be some
kind of timeless quantum field,
...such as this postulated by
...certain models in quantum cosmology?
Or possibly, it could be an
immaterial entity driven by instinct,
...such as the 'guṇas' from Hindu philosophy.
Or maybe it could be a metaphysical force,
...like the 'dao' from Chinese philosophy.
Or perhaps it could be abstract
information with causal powers,
...as scholars like Paul Davies have recently argued.
Or, just as likely,
...it could be something else entirely
that we haven't even conceived of yet.
Craig relies entirely
...on his own personal intuition,
...that a personal agent is the only sort of thing
...that could bring the universe into being,
...without even considering these other possibilities.
Indeed, it seems on the face of it highly unlikely
...that we humans could have
any reliable method of knowing
...what exists outside of the universe.
Yet, Craig not only claims to know this,
...but claims to have come to this conclusion
...on the basis of reflection and intuition,
...without even needing to do
...any scientific research or empirical investigation.
As such, I believe Craig's argument
...as to why the cause of
the universe must be personal
...to be entirely unpersuasive.
He seems to have no persuasive
answer to the simple question:
Why can't a non-personal, timeless entity
...be the cause of the universe?
WILLIAM (clip): Conclusion.
JAMES (narrating): Craig's Kalam cosmological argument
...faces major problems.
This could be summarized as a series of questions.
First,
...what is the temporal extent of the present?
Craig needs to provide a
cogent answer to this question
...before he can develop a philosophy of time
...that is necessary for the Kalam to work.
Second,
...how can we determine that,
...because certain situations involving
actual infinities are impossible or absurd,
...that therefore the universe
cannot be infinitely old?
This difficulty in making a leap between
...hypothetical thought experiments
and the finitude of the past
...is a major limitation of philosophical arguments
...for a beginning of the universe.
Third,
...is the notion of 'time' in general relativity
...equivalent to 'real' metaphysical time?
It seems that Craig must answer 'No' to this question
...if he is to maintain his
present philosophy of time.
And yet such an answer means that
he cannot appeal to scientific results,
...which depend on general relativity to
establish the beginning of the universe.
Fourth,
...why can't the universe
...just begin without a cause?
Craig's quip that 'from nothing, nothing comes'
...is not a sufficient answer,
...since the real question is not whether
the universe could have popped into nothing,
...but whether the universe could simply
have begun a finite time in the past
...without needing any external cause.
Fifth,
...why can't a non-personal timeless
entity be the cause of the universe?
Craig asserts that only an immaterial
mind with libertarian freedom
...can cause a temporal state to
begin from an initial timeless state,
...but he has no non-circular justification for this,
...and simply ignores the many other possible causes
...that could have brought about this effect.
Unless Craig is able to provide
...cogent and consistent answers
to these five questions,
...his Kalam cosmological argument
...will continue to be plagued
by major unresolved problems,
...and therefore fail to persuade skeptics such as me
...that God is the best explanation
for the origin of the universe.
PAUL (narrating): That's just the short version.
For an incredibly detailed scholarly breakdown
...of all of Dr. Craig's most popular arguments,
...check out James' book
'Unreasonable Faith:'
'How William Lane Craig'
'Overstates the Case for Christianity',
...or at least subscribe to his YouTube channel,
...where James analyzes the latest apologetics.
Or the next time you have
...eight hours to spare,
...might I recommend his full-length
...Kalam-argument collaboration with Digital Gnosis?
Every video may begin to exist,
...but some continue into future infinite.
Until next time.
WILLIAM (clip): Well, thank you very much
...for coming and sharing this time, this evening.
PAUL (narrating): Later.